U.S. President's Railroad Commission Photographs 5003 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series XX: U.S. President's Railroad Commission
  This series contains photographs of the U.S. President's Railroad Commission members, proceedings, and certain exhibits from the hearings. Of note is the photograph of the commission members in the Oval Office with President Dwight D. Eisenhower.
  - Sheldon R. Lewis (Box 61, Folder 2)
    Manager, Traffic Services, General Electric Co.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Commission In Session, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 2)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Commission In Session, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 3)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Portrait of Commission Members, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 4)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Commission In Session, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 5)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Commission In Session, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 6)
    H. H. Franklin, LIRR and BLF&E.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Portrait of Commission Members, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 7)
    - Item 0: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Models of Railroad Signals Used As Exhibits Before Commission, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 8)
    "We use these in our own Long Island school for firemen." - H. H. Franklin, LIRR and BLF&E
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 8)
  - Models of Railroad Signals Used As Exhibits Before Commission, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 9)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 9)
  - Large Scale Model Diesel Electrical Locomotive, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 10)
    Used as exhibit before Commission.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 10)
  - Portrait of Commission with the President, 1960 (Box 63, Folder 11)
    In Oval Office with President Dwight D. Eisenhower.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 11)
- Series XXI: Pennsylvania Railroad: Enola Yards, Rutherford Yards, Harrisburg Penn Station
  This series consists of photographs of the Pennsylvania Railroad's facilities in Harrisburg, Pennsylvania. These photographs were submitted to the Commission as Employees' Exhibit 6, are referred to by the letter H in testimony, and were taken by J.H. Ritchie. Mr. Ritchie was employed as a fireman and engineer for the Pennsylvania Railroad, working in both road and yard service, assigned to work the Enola Yards. The Pennsylvania Railroad was a class I railroad operating in the Mid-Atlantic and Midwestern United States, with its headquarters in Pennsylvania. This series document's the PRR's facilities in and around Harrisburg. This includes the Enola Yards, which was the largest freight yard in the world until 1956. The Enola Yards contained a diesel locomotive shop, a 43-stall roundhouse, two hump classification yards, and 145 miles of track. The Enola Yards were electrified in 1938, and the pictures in this series show some of those power lines. This series also contains photographs of the Harrisburg Penn Station, one of many of the stations and terminals built by the PRR. This station was built in 1887 and is a designated National Historic Landmark.
  - Harrisburg Penn Station, 1960 (Box 53, Folder 155)
    Taken from the Mulberry Street overhead bridge
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 155)
  - Freight Yard and Caboose Tracks, 1960 (Box 53, Folder 193)
    Taken at the extreme west end of the Enola Yard, looking eastward. Large number of crossovers and leader ladder tracks. To left of telephone pole are two switch engines working on same ladder.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 53, Folder 193)
  - Electric engine, 1961 (Box 55, Folder 143)
    Pennsylvania Railroad Electric Unit #4851
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 143)
  - Units at Rutherford Engine House on Reading Railroad Track, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 30)
    View of ALCO and Fairbanks Morse units coupled in multiple operation preparatory to leaving Rutherford engine house. Note exceptional difference between height of end plates between units and dangers encountered when passing from left to right while locomotive is in motion.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 30)
  - View of Enola Yards Looking South, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 31)
    View of Enola Yard looking south. Large building left of center is the steel car shop. In center of picture is the hump, beyond that the classification yard. Employee parking lot shown; employees must cuss tracks to get to car repair shop.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 31)
  - Enola Yards Looking East, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 32)
    Enola yards looking eastward from west of engine house (center background of photo) at the receiving yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 32)
  - Enola Engine House, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 33)
    Close up view of Enola engine house showing lower end of ready tracks. Engines prepared for departure eastbound. Note diversity of motive power which engine crews must familiarize themselves with.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 33)
  - Extreme West End of Enola Yards looking Eastward, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 34)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 34)
  - Interlocking Plant at Harrisburg Penn Station, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 35)
    Interlocking as seen from Mulberry Street bridge looking eastward.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 35)
  - Interlocking Plant at West End of Harrisburg Penn Station, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 36)
    View of state interlocking at west end of Harrisburg passenger station. Electric locomotive at right of picture is being moved by engine crew from ready track to station in preparation for hauling passenger tram to N.Y. Reverse movements thru interlocking require man on left side to relay signal indications to engineer. Loco No. 4851 (type G-G-1).
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 36)
  - Interlocking Plant at West End of Harrisburg Penn Station, 1960 (Box 57, Folder 37)
    View of state interlocking taken from State St. overhead bridge looking eastward into Harrisburg passenger station. Storage tracks are at left with reading station beyond. Signals governing movements in this area are mostly low home position light type. Overhead catanery system provides current at 11,000 volts for electric operation.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 57, Folder 37)
  - Harrisburg Penn Station, 1960 (Box 63, Folder 102)
    Photograph if the Pennsylvania passenger station. PRR Unit No. 4935, electric locomotive. Overhead wires carry 11,000 volts.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 102)
  - Enola Yards Looking East, 1960 (Box 63, Folder 103)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 103)
  - Harrisburg Penn Station, 1960 (Box 63, Folder 104)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 104)
  - View of Enola Yards Looking South, 1960 (Box 63, Folder 106)
    View of Enola Yard looking south. Large building left of center is the steel car shop. In center of picture is the hump, beyond that the classification yard. Employee parking lot shown; employees must cross tracks to get to car repair shop.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 63, Folder 106)
- Series XXII: Pennsylvania Railroad: Philadelphia Division
  This series consists of photographs of the Pennsylvania Railroad's facilities in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania These photographs were submitted to the Commission as Employees' Exhibit 35, are referred to by the letter F in testimony, and were taken by Edward J. Bartley. Mr. Bartley was employed locomotive fireman on the Pennsylvania Railroad, and was a member of Lodge 75 of the BLF&E. The Pennsylvania Railroad was a class I railroad operating in the Mid-Atlantic and Midwestern United States, with its headquarters in Pennsylvania. The photographs in this series document the operations of the PRR in Philadelphia, primarily its service to numerous industries in the two mile radius around the Grays Ferry Yard. In addition to documenting the operations and movements of trains, this series also documents a sizeable portion of Philadelphia city streets in 1960.
  - Looking South from Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    Looking south in Gray's Ferry Yard. All the tracks shown in the picture start within the yard and then they cross 49th Street, which is a heavily traveled road. Traffic does not always stop at the railroad tracks crossing, so a lookout on both side is necessary. Traffic is so heavy because of fuel oil companies located at foot of 49th Street.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 3)
  - Looking South from Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 4)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 5)
    Exhibits F-29 through F-29e show general traffic conditions on Delaware Avenue in the vicinity of Oregon Avenue. Note the very heavy volume of large trucks, tractors, and trailers and passenger automobiles and buses. It also shows that there is no traffic pattern. Vehicles move in any direction.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 5)
  - Midvale Yard, Looking East, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 6)
    Photographs F-42 through F-42d were taken in Midvale yard, looking to the east. Note the curvature of the tracks. ENgines working th yard are all headed east, placing the curves on the fireman's side of locomotive. Close clearances and obstructions throughout yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 6)
  - Midvale Yard, Looking East, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 7)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 7)
  - Delaware River, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 8)
    Police boats
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 8)
  - Delaware River, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 9)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 9)
  - Delaware River, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 10)
    Tug boat, ships, police wagon
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 10)
  - Delaware Avenue, Night Shot, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 68)
    Engine continues to move northward on Delaware Avenue. Note southbound traffic passing on fireman's side.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 68)
  - Midvale Yard, Facing East, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 69)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 69)
  - Delaware Avenue, Looking North, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 70)
    Engine moves towards industrial siding on Delaware Avenue.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 70)
  - Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 71)
    A general view of the Grays Ferry Yard, taken from 49th Street Bridge. Note that several of the tracks have overhead electric wires. These lines carry 11,000 volts. The power lines are from two and a half to about eight feet above the tops of the cars.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 71)
  - Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 72)
    View of Gray's Ferry Yard looking northward from 49th Street. Picture F-1 and this picture were taken from opposite sides of the railroad. Note the maze of tracks curving both left and right.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 72)
  - North End of Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 73)
    This picture was taken from the overhead bridge shown in pictures F-1 & F-1A. The view is Northward showing the North End of Gray's Ferry Yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 73)
  - Gray's Ferry Yard Track Curvature, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 74)
    View is southward at Gray's Ferry Yard. To the extreme left is the Engine Storage Yard. Immediately behind the water tower see No. 20, No. 21 and No. 22 yard tracks. To the right of these tracks are the "B" yard tracks No. 1, No. 2, No. 3, & No. 4. The GS-4 type engine is on the Running Track Curve. Caboose is standing on the Caboose Track. On the immediate right are the yard tracks No. 18 to No. 8. Engines assigned to work this yard are all headed north. The engine shown in the picture headed south is from another district and has come over to pick up some cars.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 74)
  - Looking South from Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 75)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 75)
  - Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 77)
    View of 49th Street looking northward. Note the remains of what was once a crossing warning sign (on telephone pole). There is no warning to traffic about railroad crossing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 77)
  - South End of Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 78)
    General view of the South End of Gray's Ferry Yard. Notic eth ehow the tracks curve both to the left and right throughout the yard. Notice also the two crossovers shown in the center of the picture. Such conditions require constant lookout.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 78)
  - Gray's Ferry Yard, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 80)
    View looking southward at Gray's Ferry Yard. Track on extreme left leads into Cities Service Oil Co. and also downhill to Botanic Avenue, where we service Firestone Co. and the Allied Oil Co. The gondola is standing on No. 2 East Side. Next to that is No. 1 East Side. Track in forefront is the Bridge Track which leads over the Schuylkill River Bridge to Gray's Ferry Ave. Note: The bridge track crosses the Engine Yard Lead, the lead to No. 20, No. 21 and No. 22 yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 80)
  - Caboose on Wye Track, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 81)
    View is Eastward toward Schuylkill River. Caboose is standing on the Wye track. The track has a sharp curve and when the engine approaches headed east the signal and smash-board are sen first by the fireman and not by the engineer unti lhe is almost on top of them. The signal and smash-board protect the drawbridge beyond. Fixed signal and banner govern movement onto the drawbridge.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 81)
  - Gray's Ferry Avenue Bridge Abutment, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 82)
    Picture was taken from the abutment of Gray's Ferry Avenue overhead bridge. This abutment obstructs the view of engine crews coming off the Engine Yard Storage Tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 82)
  - Girard Point Yard from Engineer's Side of Cab, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 83)
    Picture was taken from the Engineer's window. All Engines working in this yard are headed East. Hood of engine obstructs engineer's view.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 83)
  - Girard Point Yard from Engineer's Side of Cab, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 84)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 84)
  - View from the Fireman's Side of Cab, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 85)
    View from the Fireman's Window of the same engine in pictures F-10 and 11. Notice the radically different view the fireman has from that of the engineer. The entire yard may be seen buy the fireman, while the engineer can see nothing.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 85)
  - Girard Point Yard Looking West, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 86)
    Picture looking westward Girard Point. Men at right are loading a hopper car with a mobile crane.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 86)
  - Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 87)
    Picture shows a GS-4 type locomotive moving southward on Delaware Ave. Note traffic moving in same direction on the fireman's side of the locomotive. Due to the curvature in the track, the engine moves toward the oncoming traffic.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 87)
  - Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 88)
    Picture shows locomotive continuing to move southward as traffic continues to move on both sides. Truck is passing the engineers side of the engine. Automobiles are preparing to come around the fireman's side of engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 88)
  - Inside cab, looking at Fireman from Engineer's Seat, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 89)
    Fireman looking southward, in the direction of the movement. Note: Fireman has hand on emergency valve prepared to apply brakes if necessary.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 89)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 90)
    View from the fireman's window of Delaware Avenue. This is what the fireman saw when looking ahead in exhibit F-16. Note the Overland Company truck to the left of the safety island
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 90)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 91)
    Note Overland Company truck crossing from the east to the west side of Delaware Ave. This movement was spotted by the fireman due to the fact that it was made from his side of the engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 91)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 92)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 92)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 93)
    Movement of engine continues southward. Note that the Overland Company truck has progressed further westward, turning in front of the train.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 93)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 94)
    Movement of engine continues southward. Note poultry truck preparing to make turn and go north. Truck has stopped in path of engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 94)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 95)
    Engine continues to move southward. Note large truck trailer is about to halt for traffic signal in the path of the train.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 95)
  - View from Fireman's Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 96)
    Engine continues to move southward. Note large truck trailer has halted for traffic signal and meanwhile, an automobile has come from the Engineer's side of the engine and has halted behind the truck.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 96)
  - View from Cab's Rear Window, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 97)
    Engine comes to a halt, picture is taken through rear window showing route over which engine has just traveled. Note the large volume of traffic coming south behind the train.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 97)
  - Delaware Avenue and Pier 78, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 98)
    View looking Southward from Pier 78. Note automobiles are parked on rail leading to Pier 78.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 98)
  - Delaware Avenue and Pier 80, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 99)
    View looking southward from Pier 80. Note automobiles, trucks and bushes obstruct vision of engine crew. Note also, curvature in tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 99)
  - Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 100)
    Engine moving north with cut of cars. Note curvature of tracks, automobiles on tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 100)
  - Delaware Avenue Track to Pier 84, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 101)
    Picture of track leading to Pier No. 84. Note skates piled up in front of loading platform, which obstruct vision of engine crew. Note immediately inside gate is an opening in the wall, there is a similar opening in the opposite wall. Stevedores operate self propelled loading equipment through these openings, creating a dangerous conditions.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 101)
  - Delaware Avenue Track to Pier 84, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 102)
    Picture of track leading to Pier No. 84. Note skates piled up in front of loading platform, which obstruct vision of engine crew. Note immediately inside gate is an opening in the wall, there is a similar opening in the opposite wall. Stevedores operate self propelled loading equipment through these openings, creating a dangerous conditions. Slightly different angle to Exhibit F-21; note truck that is about to cross the tracks.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 102)
  - Traffic Headed North On Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 103)
    Heavily traveled road.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 103)
  - Industry Siding, Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 104)
    Engine moving out of siding on Delaware Avenue. Note traffic moving northward, approaching from fireman's side.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 104)
  - Engine leaving North End of Pier 84 Onto Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 105)
    Engine moving out of the north end of Pier No. 84 yard, onto Delaware Ave. Note traffic continues to keep moving despite engine movement.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 105)
  - Engine at North End of Pier 84 Onto Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 106)
    Engine has stopped movement, and prepares to back second car in draft into yard.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 106)
  - Engine at North End of Pier 84 Onto Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 107)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 107)
  - Engine Backing Car Onto Pier 84 from Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 108)
    Crew now has a hold of one car and is backing down toward Pier 84 yard. Note traffic continues to move. Note weeds make it difficult to ascertain position of switches. PRR Unit 9121
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 108)
  - Brakeman Throwing Switch on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 110)
    Brakeman preparing to throw a switch on Delaware Ave. Because of the heavy volume of traffic, it is essential for the fireman and engineer to keep an eye out for the brakeman's safety
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 110)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 111)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 111)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 112)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 112)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 113)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 113)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 114)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 114)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 115)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 115)
  - General Traffic Conditions on Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 116)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 116)
  - Moving North On Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 117)
    Engine moving northward on Delaware Avenue at night. Picture taken from fireman's window. Note poor lighting conditions. Note further that truck has moved into the path of the engines movement.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 117)
  - Moving North On Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 118)
    Engine continues to move northward on Delaware Ave. Note automobile moving into path of engine on fireman's side.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 118)
  - Locomotive Pushing Car North On Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 119)
    Both of these pictures show engine pushing a car north on Delaware Avenue. Traffic moving southbound passes on fireman's side of engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 119)
  - Locomotive Pushing Car North On Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 120)
    Both of these pictures show engine pushing a car north on Delaware Ave. Traffic moving southbound passes on fireman's side of engine.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 120)
  - Locomotive Pushing Car North On Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 121)
    Engine pushing car north on Delaware Ave. Note truck parked at curb. Fireman is in a position to determine the clearance on this move.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 121)
  - Engine Pulling Cars South, Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 122)
    Engine pulling cars southward on Delaware Ave. Note the way in which the cars are stretched out on an "S" curve. In this case, only the fireman has a view of the last car in the train. Also note the heavy traffic in this area.
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 122)
  - Engine Pulling Cars South, Delaware Avenue, 1960 (Box 55, Folder 123)
    - Item 1: Click for Image (Box 55, Folder 123)